<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: Social Media | Alexey Zagalsky]]></title>
  <link href="http://alexeyza.com/blog/categories/social-media/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://alexeyza.com/"/>
  <updated>2016-05-06T10:59:24-07:00</updated>
  <id>http://alexeyza.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Alexey Zagalsky]]></name>
    <email><![CDATA[alexeyza@gmail.com]]></email>
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Supporting the Contributing Student]]></title>
    <link href="http://alexeyza.com/blog/2016/05/04/student-experiences-using-github-in-se-courses/"/>
    <updated>2016-05-04T21:26:38-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://alexeyza.com/blog/2016/05/04/student-experiences-using-github-in-se-courses</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>The modern ecosystem of tools and channels students use to support their learning is quite elaborate. For example, in a course we recently taught, <em>GitHub</em> was used to host and disseminate the course material; <em>Moodle</em> was used for assignment submission and for posting grades; For private communication students used <em>email</em>, and for group communication and class discussion they used <em>Slack</em>; For collaborating on files <em>Google Drive</em> or <em>Dropbox</em> were used; and for managing and coordinating tasks students used <em>Trello</em>.</p>

<center><img style="margin: 8px 20px" src="http://alexeyza.com/images/student_ecosystem_tools.png" height="360" title="Student ecosystem of tools and channels"/></center>


<p>If we consider the learner&rsquo;s needs, we could say that the most <strong>basic needs</strong> (i.e., hosting and disseminating course materials, facilitating communication, and supporting evaluation) can be satisfied by Moodle and email. And then tools like <em>Google Drive</em>, <em>Dropbox</em>, <em>Slack</em>, and <em>Trello</em> support the learner&rsquo;s <strong>collaborative needs</strong>, while tools like <em>GitHub</em> and <em>Stack Overflow</em> support the learner&rsquo;s <strong>participatory needs</strong>.</p>

<p>In this post, we&rsquo;d like to focus on <em>GitHub</em>.</p>

<!--more-->


<h2>Student Experiences Using GitHub in SE Courses</h2>

<p>We <a href="/pdf/cscw15.pdf">previously studied</a> <strong>How</strong> and <strong>Why</strong> educators use GitHub and we found that the use of GitHub provides many benefits. GitHub supports and encourages <strong>knowledge co-construction</strong> and allows reuse and sharing of materials. It provides transparency of activity, and promotes collaboration while fostering a <strong>participatory culture</strong> where students act not only as &ldquo;consumers&rdquo; but also as &ldquo;contributors&rdquo;. And the use of GitHub also provides <strong>applied benefits</strong>, in the form of industry relevant skills and practices.</p>

<p>We <a href="/blog/2015/09/10/embracing-participatory-culture-in-education/">shared these findings with the community</a> and discovered that many other educators have adopted the use of GitHub (each in their own way). However, until now we haven&rsquo;t considered the student&rsquo;s perspective. More specifically <strong>how do students benefit</strong> from using GitHub in their courses, <strong>what challenges do students face</strong> when GitHub is used, and <strong>what recommendations can we give instructors</strong> who plan to use GitHub.</p>

<p>Thus, we set out to explore the student experiences when using GitHub in software engineering courses.</p>

<h2>Our Study</h2>

<p>We recruited a university instructor that was about to teach two different software engineering courses offered in the same semester: a Distributed Systems course aimed at both undergraduate and graduate students, and a Software Evolution course for senior undergraduate students. The distributed systems course covered topics surrounding distributed systems and included concepts such as design considerations, fault tolerance, and cloud computing. The software evolution course covered the development of large-scale systems and how software evolves over its lifetime.</p>

<center><img style="margin: 8px 20px" src="http://alexeyza.com/images/icse_seet_16_participants.png" height="300" title="Study participants"/></center>


<p>Both courses were similar in size (34 in distributed systems, 29 in software evolution) and learning activities (weekly labs, two course projects). The course projects were done either individually or collaboratively with others (in groups of 2-4 students). Projects were open-ended and students could choose what they created, what topics they addressed, and what technologies and languages they utilized. Students were required to make their work publicly available so that other people, both inside and outside the course, could view their projects. While not mandated, the overwhelming majority of students opted to use GitHub to host their projects. The instructor did not formally introduce GitHub to the students, so those unfamiliar with the tool had to learn from others or teach themselves.</p>

<p>For the first phase of the study, we conducted a preliminary interview with the instructor in order to obtain context on how they were planning to use GitHub. Then, after the students have submitted their first course project, we conducted the main part of our study where we interviewed students. In total, we interviewed 19 students &mdash; 12 students from the distributed systems course, 6 from the software evolution course, and 1 student who was taking both courses. We concluded this phase with interviewing the instructor.</p>

<p>Informed by the findings from the previous phase, and by obtaining additional context from the students' project repositories on GitHub, we composed and deployed a validation survey. 33 students answered the survey (not necessarily the same students that were interviewed previously).</p>

<h2>How was GitHub used in these courses?</h2>

<p>In both courses, GitHub was used for hosting and disseminating course materials, and for hosting student projects. Additionally, GitHub &lsquo;issue&rsquo; feature was used to facilitate lab work and discussions.</p>

<p>However, GitHub was NOT used to completely replace the university&rsquo;s learning management system (i.e., Moodle) &mdash; private discussions and grades were still hosted on Moodle. Furthermore, advanced use cases of GitHub to support learning were not utilized, e.g., the use of Pull Requests for assignment submission, or the use of continues integration tools for auto-grading.</p>

<h2>The contributing student</h2>

<p>Enabling cross-team collaboration and contributions:
<blockquote><p><em>&ldquo;I believe that one other group decided for project 2 to use [our project 1] and they made a couple of pull requests.&rdquo;</em></p><footer><strong>SE10</strong></footer></blockquote></p>

<p><blockquote><p><em>&ldquo;I thought [peer reviews] was the best way to learn&hellip;&rdquo;</em></p><footer><strong>SE11</strong></footer></blockquote></p>

<p>Student contributions to course content:
<blockquote><p><em>&ldquo;I like being able to fix the mistakes that [the course instructor] might make&hellip; because it makes me feel a little more involved.&rdquo;</em></p><footer><strong>SE1</strong></footer></blockquote></p>

<h2>Breaking the &ldquo;walled garden&rdquo;</h2>

<p>Students find mentors &ldquo;upstream&rdquo; [John Britton 2015]</p>

<p><blockquote><p><em>&ldquo;These are just people in the community I&rsquo;ve been talking to about how to do different things, and they&rsquo;ve been giving me suggestions.&rdquo;</em></p><footer><strong>SE1</strong></footer></blockquote></p>

<p><blockquote><p><em>&ldquo;I need to get them to engage with the community in a broader sense. And I think that&rsquo;s critical, and that&rsquo;s what GitHub has.&rdquo;</em></p><footer><strong>Course Instructor</strong></footer></blockquote></p>

<h2>Gaining and Demonstrating Industry Relevant Skills and Practices</h2>

<p><blockquote><p><em>&ldquo;I think when you go and work in software development, you should get used to [having] lots of eyes being all over your work; that&rsquo;s just the way it&rsquo;s gonna be, so it&rsquo;s practice before real life.&rdquo;</em></p><footer><strong>SE8</strong></footer></blockquote></p>

<p><blockquote><p><em>&ldquo;I think all three companies that I applied to this semester wanted me to link to my GitHub.&rdquo;</em></p><footer><strong>SE6</strong></footer></blockquote></p>

<h2>The Perils of Public Projects</h2>

<p><blockquote><p><em>&ldquo;It would actually be nice if [our projects] were separate or private somehow so I wouldn&rsquo;t have to go through everything and sanitize all the stuff&hellip; &rdquo;</em></p><footer><strong>SE6</strong></footer></blockquote></p>

<p><blockquote><p><em>&ldquo;The final product I&rsquo;m happy to show [employers], but all those steps getting there, they&rsquo;re often filled with pitfalls and horrible programming and badly factored code.&rdquo;</em></p><footer><strong>SE6</strong></footer></blockquote></p>

<h2>Unfamiliarity with Git and GitHub</h2>

<p>Many students were unfamiliar with Git &amp; GitHub&rsquo;s features</p>

<p>The instructor&rsquo;s lack of experience with using GitHub made it difficult to educate the students on its features, causing frustration</p>

<h2>Notification Overload</h2>

<p><blockquote><p><em>&ldquo;It sent me a million emails&hellip; I should have just turned that off, but I was worried about missing something. Because every time someone would post, you would get another email&hellip;<br/>I actually did not read anyone else&rsquo;s feedback because it was just so many emails, to be totally honest.&rdquo;</em></p><footer><strong>SE10</strong></footer></blockquote></p>

<h2>GitHub is Not Designed for Education</h2>

<p>GitHub struggles to meet some basic needs, e.g., gradebook and formal assignment submission features.</p>

<p><blockquote><p><em>&ldquo;I think one drawback of GitHub is that you cannot actually see the diff [of ] commonly used files such as PPTs or PDFs, so you can&rsquo;t really use it for correcting professor&rsquo;s slides, or PDFs.”</em></p><footer><strong>SE12</strong></footer></blockquote></p>

<h2>Planning to use GitHub in your course - here are Recommendations for SE Instructors</h2>

<p><strong>Promote the desired workflow</strong>
otherwise potential benefits might be missed</p>

<p><strong>Familiarize yourself with GitHub</strong>
know the possibilities (e.g., private vs. public repos),
take advantage of existing tools and guides (e.g., GitHub classroom, Elliot Blackburn&rsquo;s guide, or  Paul Hibbitts' course hub CMS package)</p>

<p><strong>Use supported formats</strong>
such as plain text file formats (e.g., Markdown)</p>

<h2>What is our next step?</h2>

<p>We began to study what <strong>benefits</strong> and <strong>challanges</strong> of using Slack in software engineering courses.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Embracing Participatory Culture in Education]]></title>
    <link href="http://alexeyza.com/blog/2015/09/10/embracing-participatory-culture-in-education/"/>
    <updated>2015-09-10T11:41:54-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://alexeyza.com/blog/2015/09/10/embracing-participatory-culture-in-education</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><img style="float:right; margin: 8px 20px" src="http://alexeyza.com/images/github_student.png" widht="120" height="180" title="GitHub logo owned by GitHub, Inc."/></p>

<p><blockquote><p><em>&ldquo;It&rsquo;s always about timing. If it&rsquo;s too soon, no one understands. If it&rsquo;s too late, everyone&rsquo;s forgotten.&rdquo;</em></p><footer><strong>Anna Wintour</strong></footer></blockquote></p>

<p>GitHub is on the brink of growing from a platform for software projects, and into a mainstream collaboration platform for other domains as well.
An unexpected area where GitHub&rsquo;s collaborative <strong>workflow</strong> holds the potential to bring groundbreaking changes is education and learning. In fact, educators have already begun to use GitHub to support teaching and learning. In some cases using it to replace certain aspects of the traditional learning management systems (e.g., Blackboard, Moodle), while in other cases gaining new benefits and capabilities.</p>

<!--more-->


<h2>Beyond Software Development</h2>

<p><a href="https://github.com/">GitHub</a> is a popular Web-based social code sharing service that utilizes the Git distributed version control system. The software development community has <a href="http://www.wired.com/2015/03/github-conquered-google-microsoft-everyone-else">embraced GitHub</a> as an essential platform for managing their software projects. After just seven years, GitHub has 9 million registered users, and about 20 million unregistered visitors. Similarly, tools such as <a href="https://bitbucket.org/">BitBucket</a> and <a href="https://about.gitlab.com/">GitLab</a> gain popularity in hosting software projects. More importantly, GitHub is far more than a code repository, it is a social meeting place, that supports <a href="http://wenger-trayner.com/introduction-to-communities-of-practice/">communities of practice</a> and fosters collaboration. People use it as a virtual meeting place, that supports discussions, and allows everyone to maintain awareness.</p>

<p>However, GitHub is not just for software development. We believe it is similar to other tools that are built for developers (e.g., Wiki, Stack Overflow), but end up being <a href="http://allankelly.blogspot.ca/2014/04/the-prototype-of-future-knowledge.html">adopted by other knowledge workers</a>. Early adopters use GitHub to <a href="http://readwrite.com/2013/11/08/seven-ways-to-use-github-that-arent-coding">compose music</a>, to <a href="http://venturebeat.com/2013/01/30/github-for-recipes-brings-open-source-into-the-kitchen/">share recipes</a>, and even for legal documents. For example, Stefan Wehrmeyer, a German software developer and activist has posted the <a href="https://github.com/bundestag/gesetze">German federal government&rsquo;s laws and regulations</a> to GitHub. Allowing anyone to track changes, see who made the changes, and why. Thus, not only providing traceability of the changes, but with the use of GitHub&rsquo;s diff functionality showing what exactly has been changed. Similarly, the <a href="https://github.com/divegeek/uscode">US federal code</a> and the <a href="https://github.com/steeve/france.code-civil">French civil code</a> have been published to GitHub as well.</p>

<p>In addition to these marvelous uses, GitHub is used for educational purposes.</p>

<h2>Our Study</h2>

<p>My fellow researchers and I studied <strong>How</strong> and <strong>Why</strong> educators use GitHub. As a first phase, we searched for resources (such as blog posts and discussion groups) that described the personal experiences of educators using GitHub to support learning or teaching.</p>

<p>Next, we interviewed 15 educators that have used GitHub, including one of the blog authors from the previous phase. We were able to thoroughly investigate the <strong>usefulness</strong> and <strong>potential</strong> of GitHub in education. We then proceeded to interview John Britton, a representative from GitHub, in order to gain insights into GitHub&rsquo;s perspective.</p>

<p>And finally, we conducted a follow-up survey to get feedback on our interpretation of the interview findings.</p>

<h2>Why Educators Use GitHub</h2>

<p>Traditional learning management systems (LMS) are a pain point for many educators (including myself). The basic purpose of these systems is to allow educators to share course material with the students, and to host student assignments. However, in reality, we end up using a combination of LMSs, and external services, while somehow most of the communication happens over email.</p>

<p>On top of that, access to the course material or the assignments is limited to current students only. Which doesn&rsquo;t include students who completed the course and want to reuse the material, other educators, or industry people who may share their own experience. This is not a hypothetical situation, I&rsquo;ve seen this happen first hand, more than once (both as a student and as an educator).</p>

<p>GitHub may not solve all these problems, but our study reveals <strong>extraordinary benefits</strong> to educators who used it.</p>

<h3>Reuse and Sharing of Knowledge</h3>

<p>By using GitHub, educators can share and collaborate on course material. When a fellow educator wants to teach a similar course, all that she needs to do is <a href="https://help.github.com/articles/fork-a-repo/">fork</a> the original course on GitHub. And if she improves it, other educators are aware of the changes and can integrate them back to their courses as well.</p>

<p><blockquote><p><em>&ldquo;Some of the material is shared with the world and some of it is shared with other instructors of other universities&hellip;We&rsquo;re versioning all of it.&rdquo;</em></p><footer><strong>CS professor from University of California at Berkeley</strong></footer></blockquote></p>

<p>Furthermore, one of the interviewees shared the following unexpected situation:</p>

<p><blockquote><p><em>&ldquo;I think the repository has something like 200 stars on GitHub right now and as far as I can tell most of those stars are from people who didn&rsquo;t take the course.&rdquo;</em></p><footer><strong>CS instructor from Harvard University</strong></footer></blockquote></p>

<p>Suddenly, the course grows beyond the classroom, allowing the exchange of ideas and knowledge among students and external people (e.g., practitioners and experts from the industry).</p>

<h3>Transparency of Activity</h3>

<p>Using GitHub as a submission platform also makes it easier for educators to monitor student progress, activity, and participation. GitHub has numerous features that support transparency of student activities, e.g., <a href="https://help.github.com/articles/about-repository-graphs/">graphs</a> and the <a href="https://help.github.com/articles/news-feed/">news-feed</a> that aggregates all the activity in one place.</p>

<p><blockquote><p><em>&ldquo;[As an educator] you really see the full history of how the document comes into being, including all the discussions, the former versions. I can monitor who&rsquo;s active, working in certain teams, which is also handy, practical.&rdquo;</em></p><footer><strong>CS professor from Delft University of Technology</strong></footer></blockquote></p>

<h3>Encourage Participation</h3>

<p>By using GitHub educators were able to encourage participation. In one case, the instructor used student logs as material for discussion in class. Another example was where students submitted an <a href="https://guides.github.com/features/issues/">issue</a> followed by a <a href="https://guides.github.com/introduction/flow/">Pull-Request</a>, mechanisms that are usually used to discuss bugs or code changes, in order to change a deadline.</p>

<p><blockquote><p><em>&ldquo;Last year, I introduced a number of deadlines in between, and the time of the deadline was always Friday evening. And the students didn&rsquo;t like it, so they opened an issue on GitHub - "Can we move it?&rdquo;. So I said, I&rsquo;m open to suggestions, please discuss it. Everyone responded to that issue on GitHub, and then at the end I said &ldquo;based on the discussion, it is going to be on Sunday&rdquo;. And then I asked the student who initiated this discussion &ldquo;Please, open a Pull Request where you provide the fix to the assignment, so the Friday now changed to Sunday&rdquo;. And that worked really nicely.&ldquo;</em></p><footer><strong>CS professor from Delft University of Technology</strong></footer></blockquote></p>

<h3>Industry Relevance</h3>

<p>Educators also use GitHub to provide their students with industry relevant skills and tools.</p>

<p><blockquote><p><em>&ldquo;This is very much what people use these days in [statistics], and so I actually consider it a completely valid pedagogical goal in and of itself. And the fact that it makes our work together easier is a beautiful byproduct.&rdquo;</em></p><footer><strong>Statistics professor from University of British Colombia</strong></footer></blockquote></p>

<p>Furthermore, GitHub can also be used as a portfolio showcasing the student&rsquo;s work. It is common for employers to evaluate candidates based on their existing projects and activity on GitHub.</p>

<h3>Incidental Benefits</h3>

<p>There are incidental benefits as well. Educators mentioned the ease of use, where you don&rsquo;t have to use complex university systems, instead you can use your existing tools and just &ldquo;push the changes&rdquo;. Additionally, GitHub provides <a href="https://education.github.com/discount_requests/new">free academic licenses</a>, both at the &ldquo;student level&rdquo; and at the &ldquo;organization level&rdquo;.</p>

<h2>How Educators Use GitHub</h2>

<p>With <strong>course material hosted on GitHub</strong>, students (or other educators) can discuss and suggest corrections to the material with the use of Pull-Requests or issues. For example, in a course I taught, <a href="https://github.com/alexeyza/startup-programming/pulls?utf8=%E2%9C%93&amp;q=is%3Apr">students submitted corrections</a> to the material by using pull requests. We didn&rsquo;t require them to do so, and it was not part of the grade - they did it on their own. Some educators even give extra credit for accepted pull requests. This is a game changer benefit of using a system like GitHub - it improves quality and encourages collaboration, benefiting everyone.</p>

<p><img src="/images/student_pr.png" title="Students contribute to the course material" alt="alt text" /></p>

<p>Additionally, <strong>educators use GitHub as a submission platform</strong>. And there are two main ways to do it. One is more similar to the traditional LMS, where you create a separate repository per student, and it&rsquo;s private. The second way is having a single repository for the assignment, and the students will fork or branch it. This way all of the students can see each others work, allowing them to collaborate and build on the work of others.</p>

<h2>Not Quite Ready for Prime-time, Yet</h2>

<p>Our study uncovered how educators use GitHub to support learning and teaching, while extending or even replacing traditional LMSs. However, the implications of our findings go beyond GitHub itself. The emergence of GitHub&rsquo;s workflow within education is transforming the traditional e-learning model and will better support socio-collaborative learning environments of the future. I would also like to <strong>strongly recommend</strong> reading <a href="http://www.infoworld.com/article/2886828/collaboration-software/github-for-the-rest-of-us.html"><strong>GitHub for the rest of us</strong></a> by Jon Udell.</p>

<p>It should be mentioned that GitHub was not designed as an LMS, and even though it can be used as such, there are several challenges involved. The main challenges are the lack of a shared knowledge base of suggested and best practices, and the barriers to entry educators face (i.e., an understanding of Git is required).</p>

<p><blockquote><p><em>&ldquo;To get the most out of GitHub, you need to understand Git&hellip; if you use it the right way it is simple, but somehow with Git you end up with conflicts, and if you don&rsquo;t understand it, it&rsquo;s magic!&rdquo;</em></p><footer><strong>CS professor from Delft University of Technology</strong></footer></blockquote></p>

<h2>Planning to Use GitHub? Here&rsquo;s What You Should Do</h2>

<p><strong>Privacy is not all or nothing.</strong> GitHub allows for various visibility levels, depending on how you <a href="https://education.github.com/guide/repository_setup">set up the repository</a>. Make sure to explore these possibilities.</p>

<p><strong>Use Markdown when possible.</strong> A plain text file format will enable you to take advantage of the <code>diff</code> and line-commenting functionalities. And Markdown&rsquo;s markup language is very <a href="https://github.com/adam-p/markdown-here/wiki/Markdown-Cheatsheet">simple to learn</a>, while supporting stylized documents.</p>

<p><strong>Share your experience, and learn how others use GitHub.</strong> We, as a community, need your help in contributing to and shaping a shared knowledge base.</p>

<p><strong>Learn Git&rsquo;s workflow.</strong> Understanding <a href="https://www.atlassian.com/git/tutorials/comparing-workflows/gitflow-workflow">Git&rsquo;s workflow</a> (commits, branches, conflicts) will give you a better understanding how GitHub works and how it can be best used.</p>

<p><strong>Be creative.</strong> There are additional ways to enhance the teaching and learning experience. For instance, some educators use <a href="https://travis-ci.org/">Travis CI</a> for <a href="https://github.com/education/teachers/issues/3">automated assignment grading</a>.</p>

<hr />

<p>Have you used or plan to use GitHub to support teaching or learning? What was the biggest <strong>challenge</strong> for you? What <strong>recommendations</strong> do you have for other educators? Please <strong>comment</strong> below.</p>

<p><strong>P.S.</strong> <a href="https://twitter.com/alexeyzagalsky">I&rsquo;d love to meet you on Twitter.</a></p>

<p><br></p>

<h2>Published Research</h2>

<p>Additional details on this study can be found in <a href="http://alexeyza.com/pdf/cscw15.pdf">our paper</a> that was presented at the <a href="http://cscw.acm.org/2015/">CSCW 2015 conference</a>, with the <a href="https://speakerdeck.com/alexeyza/the-emergence-of-github-as-a-collaborative-platform-for-education">slides available online</a> as well. We are extremely grateful to all the interview and survey participants.</p>

<p>I would also like to thank <a href="https://margaretannestorey.wordpress.com/">Margaret-Anne Storey</a>, <a href="http://leif.me/">Leif Singer</a>, and Maryi Arciniegas Méndez for providing feedback on early versions of this post.</p>

<p>This post has been shared on <a href="http://thechiselgroup.org/2015/09/10/embracing-participatory-culture/">the CHISEL group&rsquo;s blog</a>, <a href="https://thewinnower.com/papers/2740-embracing-participatory-culture-in-education">The Winnower</a>, and on <a href="http://www.storybench.org/use-github-lessons-classroom-newsroom/">Storybench</a>.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
