<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: Social Media | Alexey Zagalsky]]></title>
  <link href="http://alexeyza.com/blog/categories/social-media/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://alexeyza.com/"/>
  <updated>2014-12-08T11:48:43-08:00</updated>
  <id>http://alexeyza.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Alexey Zagalsky]]></name>
    <email><![CDATA[alexeyza@gmail.com]]></email>
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[The Emergence of GitHub as a Collaborative Platform for Education]]></title>
    <link href="http://alexeyza.com/blog/2014/10/31/the-emergence-of-github-as-a-collaborative-platform-for-education/"/>
    <updated>2014-10-31T11:41:54-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://alexeyza.com/blog/2014/10/31/the-emergence-of-github-as-a-collaborative-platform-for-education</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<h2>Introduction here (remove when added content)</h2>

<h2>GitHub in the Classroom</h2>

<p>Using GitHub as a submission platform was accomplished in one of two ways<sup id="fnref:1"><a href="#fn:1" rel="footnote">1</a></sup>. Some interviewees set up a base repository for the class and had each student fork it&mdash;everyone who forked the base repository could see all other forked repositories as well. This allowed students to cross-reference different solutions and encouraged student collaboration (e.g., by using PRs) and peer learning.</p>

<p><blockquote><p>When you do a pull, you can see what the others in the seminar are doing. For example, a student wrote a python script, and others want to use it, so they can just grab it and use it.</p><footer><strong>[P4]</strong></footer></blockquote></p>

<p>Other interviewees set up private repositories for each student, and individual students could only see other repositories when explicitly given access. For P5&rsquo;s course, <em>Students have separate repositories, and it&rsquo;s private so that people cannot see what they are working on.</em> With this option, repositories and permissions are manually set up, which may be difficult in courses with a large number of students.</p>

<p>\subsubsection{Hosting Course Material}
Many interviewees used GitHub to host and deliver course materials [P4, P5, P8, P9, P10, P11, P12, P13, P15], including syllabi, slides, notes, reading materials, exercises and homework. It was even used to host the actual course Website, making GitHub \textit{&ldquo;a bulletin board.&rdquo;}[P10] The basic mechanism to host course Websites is by using GitHub markdown files, or for more traditional Websites, by using GitHub Pages\footnote{\url{<a href="https://pages.github.com/">https://pages.github.com/</a>}} which hosts the material directly from one&rsquo;s repository.</p>

<p>With course materials hosted on GitHub, students and other educators were able to suggest course improvements [P1, P10, P11, P12] by submitting an issue or a PR. \textit{&ldquo;Students would actually find corrections and things and they would send me Pull Requests&hellip; But there was some sense of a community that was at least, certainly invited to collaborate on the course material itself.&rdquo;}[P12] As such, interviewees were able to facilitate student contribution to the course material itself using GitHub, a use case and benefit that GitHub offers beyond many traditional systems.</p>

<h2>Motivation and Benefits</h2>

<h2>Challenges</h2>

<h2>Summary</h2>
<div class="footnotes">
<hr/>
<ol>
<li id="fn:1">
<p><a href="https://education.github.com/guide#4-set-up-the-repositories">https://education.github.com/guide#4-set-up-the-repositories</a><a href="#fnref:1" rev="footnote">&#8617;</a></p></li>
</ol>
</div>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
